Natalie Spiska: All right, perfect. Well, if you could just start by briefly explaining what current technology you use in your golf program, such as TrackMen, even what sort of stats websites you use, or even wearable technology?
Coach: Yeah, we, definitely have technology that we access. I don't know if I would call myself
Coach: an expert in all these areas. Our assistant coach does a great job with some of them, and some of them we have access to, and…
Coach: use a lot, and others we have access to and use sporadically. So, before I project expertise, I want to put a qualifier on that statement. But a few that come to mind right off the top of my head, we have Trackman, we have GC Quad, we actually use a Trackman Range.
Coach: Those would be for, like, golf swing and full shots. We have a putt-view putt lab, so we can do some putting analysis.
Coach: And, we use Stat Program, we use UpGame, and then, we also have…
Coach: Haven't been using it quite as much, because we have a new strength coach this year, but [Strength Coach] is the strength conditioning app that all of our student athletes have access to, and so…
Coach: That would be another one I guess, would technically fall in there. We don't have any wearables that we have on the guys. I think some of that's because I'm always a little nervous about the NCAA rules and what you're allowed to collect and track, but I will say…
Coach: It's probably 7 out of 9, for sure, and it could be 8 out of 9. I think there's only one that I know of doesn't wear a whoop, and our guys
Coach: constantly checking their WHOOP and talking about, you know, this, that, recovery, what have you.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, recovery scores.
Coach: Yeah, yeah, so… so we definitely do have, you know.
Coach: those pieces of technology in place, and like I mentioned, all but the WHOOP, we use them in various capacities. I could be missing some, we might be talking later in this chat here, and I'll be like, oh yeah, I forgot, we have this one too, you know, so… but those would be the primary ones that come to mind.
Natalie Spiska: You mentioned the Stats uses UpGame, is that what you called it? Yes. Have you used others like Clip Scoreboard, or Decade, or any other stats website? Is that fairly new, or have you been using that for a while?
Coach: I believe this is year 3 for us with UpGame, and it's been… it's been great. But yes, we have used others in… prior to this. We don't…
Coach: we don't double up on them, because it's a bit cumbersome for the kids to… for the players to enter, and that's half the battle, quite honestly. So we never… we would never want them to have to put in two…
Coach: different stat programs, but we landed on UpGame because of just a couple of calls that they had. I've used Golfstat long ago, I've used BirdieFire after that.
Coach: I did use Decade for a season, and then did, we've never used Clipped, but, I do think that Clipped's another one that a lot of programs are using and like, too, but UpGame's the one we're using now.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, CLIP is definitely what we're using right now, and I definitely agree. It's pretty cumbersome to put in all your stats, and yeah, it definitely takes a while, but it's interesting to hear. That's the first time I've heard from other coaches that program being used.
Natalie Spiska: But…
Coach: Of Up Game? That's the first time you've heard of Up Game?
Natalie Spiska: at least from the coaches I've, like, interviewed, but I'm not.
Coach: Yeah.
Natalie Spiska: That's, like, something that's morph in your area.
Coach: Yeah, I think UpGame was just recently purchased by TrackMan, too, so there's gonna be some overlay capabilities that's gonna make it even better,
Coach: I couldn't tell you why… oh, one other one we used for a short time, too, was called Babrassi, which they rebranded it. It's a German company. I just met the German…
Coach: like, kind of founder or, I guess the…
Coach: programmer of this Babrassi, when I was in Germany doing some recruiting, was totally impressed. And it was good, it's just… going back to your… your comment too, Natalie, the…
Coach: the,
Coach: it's just hard, because, you know, everybody on the PGA Tour, they get their stats delivered straight to them, and they don't have to go through after they've shot a 76 and go, oh, yeah, it was right here, 144 in front of the water, and then hit it, you know, over the green in the water, you know. So all that stuff comes to them, and other people, they can pay people to analyze it. We're really reliant on the self-reporting, and
Coach: if that's not accurate, then it's like, well, what are we doing anyway? You know what I mean? So, it's… there's definitely some flaws in the whole system, but I…
Coach: I think it's still important to try to hold the players accountable to that, so we can have some meaningful conversations for development in the future, too.
Natalie Spiska: And how do you think the use of your technology has, like, differed over the program, over the last few years?
Coach: Well, we built a facility here two years ago and added the Trackman range, which is really cool, because you could be hitting balls without any technology, like, right on you, and you can use the app, and there's a… there's a radar that can tell how far every shot goes, so…
Coach: you know, doing some gapping analysis, and even doing some fun, kind of competitive games, it's pretty easy to do that with the TrackMan range. I think of all the…
Coach: technologies that we use, I would say the…
Coach: I'm talking, like, the ones that you use for the game of golf, not the… I don't know how, like, to define the difference between your stat programming and your GC Quad or your Trackman, but there's obviously a massive difference, so whatever those definitions, the differences are, of the ones you're using on the turf.
Coach: I think that the GC Quad is the one we use the most, and that's because it tells you how far the ball goes.
Coach: And that's a critically important part of the game, as you know, and .
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: The more consistent we get with how our carry numbers and… and… and how, you know.
Coach: accurate we are with the prediction, accurate we are with the execution. That's where those pieces of technology come in really, really handy and useful.
Natalie Spiska: And do you think there are any other particular skill areas that technology's been useful for, such as, like, ball striking, short game, or putting, and being able to have those numbers available to you?
Coach: Well, sure, I mean, I wish I was better with the GC Quad, but I know you can use that, and the trackman for that matter, for short game and chipping, you know?
Coach: I just haven't… haven't…
Coach: I don't want to say I don't have the bandwidth to learn more about it, because I certainly do, I just… it just hasn't…
Coach: like, it hasn't happened for me yet, so I don't… I don't know how to put the GC quad down on the chipping green and have you hit a 56-degree wedge, that… that flies 6 yards, and check that spin number and go, oh, wow, you know, that's why it's…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: 2400 right now instead of 2,800, because the grass is a little wet, or… you know what I mean? Like, and knowing what spin readings are for short game shots, and what… how to create more spin, less spin on short game shots, that would be an area where I'd like to improve. Not sure if I answered the question directly, but there are certainly.
Natalie Spiska: Hmm.
Coach: you know, other pieces of technology that we're not either purchasing or know of, or even care to use. But, you know, there's definitely room to continue growing in that space, for sure.
Natalie Spiska: What I'm also interested to ask you is, obviously, coming from the Northeast, we have that entire winter period where we're stuck indoors, we're not able to get outside, whereas for you guys, you have the option of being outdoors. So how does that off-season look like for you? Do you find yourself just playing as much as you can, trying to be on grass? Or do you tend to, like, if you're working on swing, do you go indoors to work on a trackman? Or how is it like for you guys?
Coach: Much more still staying on grass, just because the winters are quite nice here, but we do have, you know, almost 6 weeks from when finals commences all the way until
Coach: you know, semester resumes, so there is still this natural, like, break, and quite honestly, it's pretty quiet around the facility during that time, because everybody goes back to their respective homes. Sometimes that means it's, you know, up to Phoenix, sometimes that means it's California. For some, it's Europe or Asia, you know what I mean?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: everybody gets a lot of unstructured practice in… in the off-season, for sure. So, I… I…
Coach: I'm a little reluctant to give you a firm answer on, like, oh yeah, we definitely do this or don't, because… and the other thing, too, which you can certainly sympathize or empathize with, is
Coach: you know, we start competing in January, and then we, you know, wrap up the NCAA postseason in May. They play summer terms June, July, August, and then we start competing against September and October. So, you know, if there is any period of time in the calendar for them to do a little bit more, just, you know.
Coach: relaxed or no practice at all, that's when that comes. So when we get to the end of October.
Coach: I don't… I don't want to say we don't do anything, but it's pretty much like, hey guys, enjoy all your time, and if you want to be out here, please use the facility, please practice, please do what you want to do, but also understand that this is… this is that time of year where it's not a bad thing for you to catch a little bit of a breather, you know?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I can… I can definitely understand that, especially since I understand the demands of playing at your guys' level as well must be so… so much, and yeah, you're constantly playing, like, even with your schedule right now, you guys are pretty much slammed, so I can definitely understand that. Maybe you just don't want to, like, play golf for a bit.
Coach: Yeah, yeah, and I don't think that's a bad thing, because absence makes the heart ponder, too, you know?
Coach: So when we do start up in January, I want you to feel good and ready to go, and I don't want you to start getting, like, man, I got, you know, I'm still hooking the ball, I can't fix this, it's April, and that's when we need you feeling, like, really excited about the postseason that's underway, you know?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah. And on your team, do you think there's a difference in certain players of how they gravitate towards technology? Like, do you think there's a certain type of personality that better, like, adapts to it, or is it, like… would you say it's the same across the board?
Coach: Oh, no, definitely. Definitely there's differences. Yeah, there's some kids that won't even hit a ball without a GC quad in front of them, and then other kids, they're, you know.
Coach: they might have it in there more because they see some of their peers doing it, but it's not, like, instinctive for them to always have a piece of technology there with them, with their training. So, definitely differences in personality, yes.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I could definitely say that I'm one of those people who needs to have that trackman there, just to see how far the ball goes, my club path and face angle, so…
Coach: Nice. Yeah, that's good.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, and just my last couple of questions, what sort of performance tools or insights do you wish exist, but don't yet? And if you can't think of anything, is there any sort of technology that you wish you could get for your team?
Coach: This might blend for both questions, but… And actually, what's funny is…
Coach: I'll give you the answer first, and then tell you. And I honestly have a theory why this is impossible. I think it would be great if…
Coach: Golf ball manufacturers would put
Coach: a GPS, either locator or sensor, inside the core, so that you could tell, like, a lot of information about, like, you would learn a lot of information about it, and all of a sudden, the need to… to try to have players put stats in, it would change, you know, like, it would go away, because if you had a ball stationary for
Coach: X number of seconds or minutes, you know, you would know, like, okay, I played my first shot from this tee to this… to this point in the fairway, the ball sat there for 6 minutes, and then it was hit again, you know what I mean?
Natalie Spiska: It would register, yeah.
Coach: Yeah, yeah, and so, I mean, if we're having a pipe dream and you're writing a nice paper about, you know, what… what technology could…
Natalie Spiska: In a perfect world, yeah.
Coach: Yeah, yeah. The reason I think they don't do that, though, if you think about it, if you hit a ball in the woods on one, and have to go into your bag, get another ball, and you hit a ball in the woods on two, and, you know, or in the tree, you know, in the weeds, or whatever, like, if you can locate your ball, and you don't ever lose balls, guess what? You don't have to buy balls, you know? So…
Coach: that's a… that's, like, a real thing, I think, with the manufacturers, you know? Like, it's like, if everybody found their ball all the time, then… Yeah, they'd be out of business. So…
Coach: Anyway, I think if you're… you know, the way that question, or at least the way I interpreted one of the two questions was, is there a technology that would be cool to have, you know, or something? So that would be something I would love to see, because
Coach: the reason I like that too, honestly, Natalie, you'll… you'll understand this. If you hit a… you know, I'll be the one that hits the bad shot, if I hit a slice…
Coach: You know, and then you're playing against me, and I'm like, hey, Natalie, I think it crossed up here, you know, and I walk all the way up there to, like, 250, you know, and we both… like, you might not even be really paying attention.
Coach: But if… if it crossed up there at 250, you're like, oh, oh, okay, yeah, if that's where you think, but… but the reality says it crossed back there at the water at, like, 175. It's just… it's just… I… I… I wish it was more…
Coach: like, I don't think I'm cheating in that sense. I mean, unless I… unless I'm trying to cheat, you know what I mean?
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: But I think it would just be really nice to not have any ambiguity on… this is where it crossed. Like, like, these are your options, because we know it crossed right here, you know what I mean? And that's… that's why I would like to see that, like, personally, but…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I think maybe not for the everyday, like, golfer, they would lose a lot of those and be a lot of money and debt, but maybe for, like, a professional, maybe a.
Coach: He could…
Natalie Spiska: he might be able to keep that in play, but yeah, it's definitely an interesting idea. I have not heard that one yet.
Coach: Yeah, yeah, so that's kind of my if-you-could-do-anything-you-want thing, and maybe that's what I would do, so… and then, can you remind me the other question? I think they kind of blended a little bit, but…
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, it was… because I asked my coach this question, he was stumped, so I was like, okay, I need to put another question just in case they can't think of it, but it was, if you could get any technology for your program, what would you choose? Like, that currently exists.
Coach: Yeah, well, we're super lucky, because we're just resourced pretty at a high level.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah.
Coach: You know what I mean? And…
Coach: And if there's something that we want bad enough, I… I probably…
Coach: could get my hands on it in some form or fashion, you know? So I would say… I don't want to say that I don't want anything else, but I… I would have to… oh, there is one, actually, there is one, because we put it… we did not have it in the… in the… we did have it in the original plans, but certain things got value engineered out just as a… as a project, you know, other expenses and stuff.
Coach: Force plates.
Natalie Spiska: Oh, yes.
Coach: force plates, I think it would be great, and to be very honest, too, I know you're recording, and hopefully this comes out right. I don't want the force plates for me, because I'm not a swing coach, I'm not the kind of guy who's like, okay, Natalie, we're gonna get you on here. Oh, wow, look and see how to dress your 60-40, we want you to get more like 55-45 on your weight, you know, transfer, or whatever. But it's more because all these pieces of technology.
Coach: Demonstrate, like, our commitment to our players and our, you know, recruiting becomes even more impressive when you have
Coach: anything you need. And we had a player from [Country] not that long ago, and that was a part of his training acumen that he liked to check. So what I want to be able to do is have a facility and, like a…
Coach: an outfit where if this is important to you, guess what? Your golf program has it here. So, that would be one that I would like to add as a force plate.
Natalie Spiska: That kind of leads into my next question, second to last, where it's what role do you see technology playing in collegiate golf in the next 5-10 years? Specifically, how it would change the recruiting process in any way? And yeah, like you mentioned, it's kind of, like, almost a way to draw in the better players of, like, hey, you should come to our program and play for us.
Coach: Yeah, I think so, for sure, and if nothing else, it just demonstrates a commitment to…
Coach: player performance, you know? And so, you, the recruit, Natalie, might not… might not care anything about TrackMan, or GC Quad, or PuttView, or any of the ones mentioned in the… in all of your research.
Coach: But, you'll probably…
Coach: feel good hearing all of that, versus the alternative, which is the program that you're also considering, which is like, no, we just work on our game, you know? We just have everybody who works on the game. It's like, well, you can measure this. If you can't measure it, you can't manage it, you know what I mean? So, like, the coaches are very committed to that, the players on the team use the technologies. I think the art in coaching is that, listen, we've got players on… on…
Coach: both ends of, you know, I got no… I don't have anybody who's zero use of technology, but, you know, we have some that are, you know, probably in the 90 percentile of all the pieces of technology we have here on using them, and some of them might be in the 50th percentile of using them. So, there's still a flexibility component of that with the way we coach our players.
Coach: But I think, you know, when it comes to collegiate athletics.
Coach: although it's changing, you know, I think sometimes we're able to access resources for our programs, and one great thing about golf is
Coach: you know, men's and women's golf. I know you guys don't have men's, but… but a lot of places have them both, and so sometimes the two coaches can work together to try to gain some resources that would otherwise be unattainable. If you have a great swing coach in your area who, you know, has all the best players working with him, he might have to save up 3, 4, 5 years to buy a trackman, and then he's got to do lessons for 3 or 4 or 5 years.
Coach: to really make it worth the investment. You know what I mean? Where we can just be like, oh, we need a second track, man? Okay, let's convince the right donor, or let's convince our administration to make this investment. You know, they're already spending several thousands, tens of thousands of dollars for other sports. If this is really important to us, let's, you know, put… present a really good argument as to why this is going to help our team perform, and if we're… if we get the approval, then boom, we have a
Coach: you know, 50,000 pieces… $50,000 piece of training, technology in our facility tomorrow, you know what I mean? So…
Coach: That's… that's what I would say.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I think, especially what I've heard from other coaches as well, the… having a men's and women's program, most of the time, the technology is shared, which is great, because I feel like that's certainly not the case in other sports that you might see. Like, it's typically very separated, so it's nice to see that there is that equality there as well.
Coach: I totally agree. Yeah, totally.
Natalie Spiska: And for my final question, overall, would you say technology has had a positive or negative impact on your program?
Coach: Oh, certainly positive. Yeah, certainly positive. I can elaborate if you want me to, but it certainly had a positive impact.
Natalie Spiska: Yeah, I think, from what you've given me, I could definitely understand why you say that's definitely positive, so…
Coach: and… Cool.
Natalie Spiska: I'll go ahead and stop recording.